<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--  
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://diggsml.org/def/stylesheets/codelists.xsl"?>
-->
<gml:Dictionary xmlns:diggs="http://diggsml.org/schemas/3.0"
    xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml/3.2" 
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://diggsml.org/schemas/3.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/DIGGSml/schema-dev/refs/heads/3.0/Diggs.xsd"
    gml:id="diggs-lrmethod-dictionary">
    
    <gml:description>
        DIGGS Standard Linear Referencing Methods Dictionary
        
        This dictionary provides a comprehensive collection of standardized Linear Referencing Methods 
        (LRMethods) for use with DIGGS linear sampling features including boreholes, wells, soundings, 
        geophysical tracklines, transects, and core samples. These methods define how positions are 
        determined and measured along linear features in compliance with ISO 19148:2021.
        
        The dictionary is organized into the following categories:
        
        1. BOREHOLE/WELL METHODS: Measured depth methods for vertical and deviated boreholes, with 
           absolute and relative positioning in both US customary (feet) and metric (meters) units.
        
        2. TRACKLINE/TRANSECT METHODS: Distance-along methods for geophysical survey lines, surface 
           transects, and traverses, supporting both absolute positioning from feature start and 
           relative positioning from intermediate referents.
        
        3. CORE SAMPLE METHODS: Specialized methods for core sample positioning accounting for:
           - Top-down measurements (standard approach when top is well-defined)
           - Bottom-up measurements (preferred when bottom provides better reference due to slough)
           - Interpolative methods for stretch/compression adjustment
        
        4. PIPELINE/INFRASTRUCTURE METHODS: Chainage and stationing methods for linear infrastructure.
        
        5. CPT SOUNDING METHODS: Penetration depth methods for cone penetration testing.
        
        Usage: These methods should be referenced in LinearSRS definitions to establish complete 
        coordinate reference systems for linear features. Users may extend this dictionary with 
        project-specific methods as needed while maintaining consistency with ISO 19148 principles.
        
        Version: 0.1
        Maintained by: DIGGS Technical Committee
        Last Updated: 2025
    </gml:description>
    
    <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/codes/DIGGS/1.0/lrmethod.xml</gml:identifier>
    <gml:name>DIGGS Linear Referencing Methods Dictionary</gml:name>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- BOREHOLE/SOUNDING METHODS - MEASURED DEPTH                       -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="md_ft">
            <gml:description>Absolute measured depth from top of borehole or sounding in feet. Measurements are cumulative 3D distance along the borehole/sounding centerline from the first coordinate (typically top of hole or rig datum) proceeding downward through the hole. Suitable for vertical, slanted, and deviated boreholes and soundings.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/crs/DIGGS/0.1/lrm.xml#md_ft</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Absolute Measured Depth (ft)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>downward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in feet from the first coordinate of the centerline LinearExtent, which represents "top of hole" (or rig datum such as kelly bushing) with positive downward along the borehole path</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="md_m">
            <gml:description>Absolute measured depth from top of borehole or sounding in meters. Measurements are cumulative 3D distance along the borehole/sounding centerline from the first coordinate (typically top of hole or rig datum) proceeding downward through the hole. Suitable for vertical, slanted, and deviated boreholes and soundings.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/crs/DIGGS/0.1/lrm.xml#md_m</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Absolute Measured Depth (m)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>downward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters from the first coordinate of the centerline LinearExtent, which represents "top of hole" (or rig datum such as kelly bushing) with positive downward along the borehole path</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="relative_md_ft">
            <gml:description>Measured depth relative to a specified referent location within a borehole or sounding in feet. The referent (e.g., ground surface, casing top, seafloor) must be defined in the LinearSRS. Positive direction is downward from the referent. Commonly used for depth below ground surface or depth below seafloor.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/crs/DIGGS/0.1/lrm.xml#relative_md_ft</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Relative Measured Depth (ft)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>relative</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>downward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in feet relative to a specified referent point (defined in LinearSRS), with positive downward from the referent location</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="relative_md_m">
            <gml:description>Measured depth relative to a specified referent location within a borehole or sounding in meters. The referent (e.g., ground surface, casing top, seafloor) must be defined in the LinearSRS. Positive direction is downward from the referent. Commonly used for depth below ground surface or depth below seafloor.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/crs/DIGGS/0.1/lrm.xml#relative_md_m</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Relative Measured Depth (m)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>relative</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>downward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters relative to a specified referent point (defined in LinearSRS), with positive downward from the referent location</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- TRACKLINE/TRANSECT METHODS - DISTANCE ALONG                  -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="distance_ft">
            <gml:description>Absolute distance along a geophysical trackline or survey transect in feet. Measurements are cumulative distance from the start of the feature (first coordinate) proceeding forward along the trackline path. Suitable for marine geophysical surveys, land transects, and linear traverses.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/crs/DIGGS/0.1/lrm.xml#distance_ft</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Absolute Distance (ft)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>forward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in feet from the first coordinate (start) of the trackline or transect LinearExtent, with positive forward along the survey line</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="distance_m">
            <gml:description>Absolute distance along a geophysical trackline or survey transect in meters. Measurements are cumulative distance from the start of the feature (first coordinate) proceeding forward along the trackline path. Suitable for marine geophysical surveys, land transects, and linear traverses.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/crs/DIGGS/0.1/lrm.xml#distance_m</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Absolute Distance (m)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>forward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters from the first coordinate (start) of the trackline or transect LinearExtent, with positive forward along the survey line</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="relative_distance_ft">
            <gml:description>Distance along trackline or transect relative to a specified referent in feet. The referent (e.g., benchmark, line intersection, waypoint) must be defined in the LinearSRS. Useful for referencing positions from intermediate control points or for tying multiple survey lines together at intersections.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/crs/DIGGS/0.1/lrm.xml#relative_distance_ft</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Relative Distance (ft)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>relative</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>forward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in feet relative to a specified referent point (defined in LinearSRS) along the trackline, with positive forward from the referent</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="relative_distance_m">
            <gml:description>Distance along trackline or transect relative to a specified referent in meters. The referent (e.g., benchmark, line intersection, waypoint) must be defined in the LinearSRS. Useful for referencing positions from intermediate control points or for tying multiple survey lines together at intersections.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/crs/DIGGS/0.1/lrm.xml#relative_distance_m</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Relative Distance (m)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>relative</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>forward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters relative to a specified referent point (defined in LinearSRS) along the trackline, with positive forward from the referent</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- CORE SAMPLE METHODS - TOP-DOWN                               -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="core_top_down_in">
            <gml:description>Absolute distance from top of core sample downward in inches. Standard method for core logging when the top of the core interval is well-defined. Measurements proceed from the top surface (first coordinate) downward through the recovered core. Used for recovered core samples that may be handled and logged separately from the parent borehole.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/crs/DIGGS/0.1/lrm.xml#core_top_down_in</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Core Top-Down Absolute (in)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>downward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in inches from the top of core (first coordinate of core LinearExtent) downward through the recovered sample</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="core_top_down_cm">
            <gml:description>Absolute distance from top of core sample downward in centimeters. Standard method for core logging when the top of the core interval is well-defined. Measurements proceed from the top surface (first coordinate) downward through the recovered core. Used for recovered core samples that may be handled and logged separately from the parent borehole.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">https://diggsml.org/def/crs/DIGGS/0.1/lrm.xml#core_top_down_cm</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Core Top-Down Absolute (cm)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>downward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters from the top of core (first coordinate of core LinearExtent) downward through the recovered sample</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- CORE SAMPLE METHODS - BOTTOM-UP                              -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="core_bottom_up_ft">
            <gml:description>Absolute distance from bottom of core sample upward in feet. Alternative method for core logging when the bottom of the core provides a better-defined reference surface than the top, commonly due to slough or disturbance at the top of the cored interval. Measurements proceed from the bottom surface (last coordinate) upward through the recovered core. The coordinate order in LinearExtent should reflect bottom-to-top direction.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">core_bottom_up_ft</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Core Bottom-Up Absolute (ft)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>upward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in feet from the bottom of core (first coordinate of bottom-up core LinearExtent) upward through the recovered sample toward the top</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="core_bottom_up_m">
            <gml:description>Absolute distance from bottom of core sample upward in meters. Alternative method for core logging when the bottom of the core provides a better-defined reference surface than the top, commonly due to slough or disturbance at the top of the cored interval. Measurements proceed from the bottom surface (last coordinate) upward through the recovered core. The coordinate order in LinearExtent should reflect bottom-to-top direction.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">core_bottom_up_m</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Core Bottom-Up Absolute (m)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>upward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters from the bottom of core (first coordinate of bottom-up core LinearExtent) upward through the recovered sample toward the top</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- CORE SAMPLE METHODS - INTERPOLATIVE                          -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="core_interpolative_ft">
            <gml:description>Interpolative positioning for core samples accounting for stretch or compression in feet. Used when the physical length of recovered core differs from the drilled interval length due to expansion (common in clay-rich soils) or compression. Requires anchor points at core top and bottom to scale positions between the physical core length and the nominal borehole depth interval. This method adjusts all intermediate positions proportionally.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">core_interpolative_ft</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Core Interpolative (ft)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>interpolative</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>downward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in feet interpolated between anchor points at core top and bottom to account for core expansion or compression relative to the drilled interval</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>true</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="core_interpolative_m">
            <gml:description>Interpolative positioning for core samples accounting for stretch or compression in meters. Used when the physical length of recovered core differs from the drilled interval length due to expansion (common in clay-rich soils) or compression. Requires anchor points at core top and bottom to scale positions between the physical core length and the nominal borehole depth interval. This method adjusts all intermediate positions proportionally.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">core_interpolative_m</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Core Interpolative (m)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>interpolative</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>downward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters interpolated between anchor points at core top and bottom to account for core expansion or compression relative to the drilled interval</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>true</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- CPT SOUNDING METHODS                                         -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="cpt_depth_ft">
            <gml:description>Absolute penetration depth for cone penetration test (CPT) soundings in feet. Measurements represent the depth of the cone tip below the ground surface or push reference level, measured along the actual penetration path (which may deviate from vertical). Positive direction is downward.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">cpt_depth_ft</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>CPT Penetration Depth (ft)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>downward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in feet of cone tip depth from ground surface (first coordinate) along the penetration path, with positive downward</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="cpt_depth_m">
            <gml:description>Absolute penetration depth for cone penetration test (CPT) soundings in meters. Measurements represent the depth of the cone tip below the ground surface or push reference level, measured along the actual penetration path (which may deviate from vertical). Positive direction is downward.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">cpt_depth_m</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>CPT Penetration Depth (m)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>downward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters of cone tip depth from ground surface (first coordinate) along the penetration path, with positive downward</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- PIPELINE/INFRASTRUCTURE METHODS                              -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="pipeline_chainage_ft">
            <gml:description>Absolute chainage or stationing along pipeline or linear infrastructure in feet. Measurements represent cumulative distance along the pipeline centerline from a defined origin point (e.g., project start, valve station, reference monument). Commonly used for pipeline integrity monitoring, inspection, and maintenance records.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">pipeline_chainage_ft</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Pipeline Chainage (ft)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>forward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in feet from the pipeline origin (first coordinate) forward along the pipeline centerline alignment</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="pipeline_chainage_m">
            <gml:description>Absolute chainage or stationing along pipeline or linear infrastructure in meters. Measurements represent cumulative distance along the pipeline centerline from a defined origin point (e.g., project start, valve station, reference monument). Commonly used for pipeline integrity monitoring, inspection, and maintenance records.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">pipeline_chainage_m</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Pipeline Chainage (m)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>forward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters from the pipeline origin (first coordinate) forward along the pipeline centerline alignment</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- TUNNEL/UNDERGROUND METHODS                                   -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="tunnel_chainage_ft">
            <gml:description>Absolute distance along tunnel alignment or underground excavation in feet. Measurements represent cumulative distance along the tunnel centerline from the defined starting point (e.g., portal, shaft, tunnel boring machine launch location). Used for tunnel geology logging, support installation records, and instrumentation positioning.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">tunnel_chainage_ft</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Tunnel Chainage (ft)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>forward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in feet from tunnel origin (first coordinate) forward along the tunnel centerline alignment</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="tunnel_chainage_m">
            <gml:description>Absolute distance along tunnel alignment or underground excavation in meters. Measurements represent cumulative distance along the tunnel centerline from the defined starting point (e.g., portal, shaft, tunnel boring machine launch location). Used for tunnel geology logging, support installation records, and instrumentation positioning.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">tunnel_chainage_m</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Tunnel Chainage (m)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>forward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters from tunnel origin (first coordinate) forward along the tunnel centerline alignment</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- WELL METHODS - ELEVATION-BASED                               -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="elevation_ft">
            <gml:description>Elevation along a borehole or well path in feet, with positive upward. Used when referencing positions by elevation rather than depth. Measurements decrease with depth into the ground. The first coordinate represents the highest elevation point (typically ground surface or casing top), and measurements decrease toward the bottom of hole.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">elevation_ft</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Elevation (ft)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>ft</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>upward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in feet as elevation values with positive upward, typically referenced to a vertical datum (e.g., NAVD88, MSL)</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

    <gml:dictionaryEntry>
        <diggs:LRMethod gml:id="elevation_m">
            <gml:description>Elevation along a borehole or well path in meters, with positive upward. Used when referencing positions by elevation rather than depth. Measurements decrease with depth into the ground. The first coordinate represents the highest elevation point (typically ground surface or casing top), and measurements decrease toward the bottom of hole.</gml:description>
            <gml:identifier codeSpace="https://diggsml.org/def/authorities.xml#DIGGS">elevation_m</gml:identifier>
            <gml:name>Elevation (m)</gml:name>
            <diggs:type>absolute</diggs:type>
            <diggs:units>m</diggs:units>
            <diggs:positiveDirection>upward</diggs:positiveDirection>
            <diggs:anchorDefinition>Measurement in meters as elevation values with positive upward, typically referenced to a vertical datum (e.g., NAVD88, MSL)</diggs:anchorDefinition>
            <diggs:requiresCalibration>false</diggs:requiresCalibration>
        </diggs:LRMethod>
    </gml:dictionaryEntry>

</gml:Dictionary>